<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>greenhouse climates on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/tags/greenhouse-climates/</link>
    <description>Recent content in greenhouse climates on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/greenhouse-climates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the equable climate problem during the Late Cretaceous greenhouse using paleosol carbonate clumped isotope temperatures from the Campanian of the Western Interior Basin, USA</title>
      <link>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warm Terrestrial Subtropics During the Paleocene and Eocene: Carbonate Clumped Isotope (Δ47) Evidence From the Tornillo Basin, Texas (USA)</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbonate Clumped Isotopes: Certainties and Uncertainties of Thermometry and Eocene Subtropical Paleoclimate</title>
      <link>/talk/wce_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/wce_seminar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenhouse climates of the Cenozoic</title>
      <link>/project/greenhouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenhouse/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Globe.png&#34; alt=&#34;Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The late Cretaceous though the early Eocene is an intriguing period of Earth history because of the geologic evidence for globally warm climates that corresponds with high concentrations of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere. Studying these high CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates can  potentially illuminate what high-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates will be like in the future. However, a couple of basic questions about these so-called greenhouse climate regimes drive the paleoclimate research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first, seemingly simple, question is: how hot was it really? One way to quantify earth surface temperatures is by using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates that formed during that time period. I used a seres of stacked paleosols from Big Bend National Park, Texas, USA to estimate air temperatures in the subtropics (30 °N).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SamplingBigYellow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My temperature estimates were intriguingly cold - I estimate summer temperatures of 32 °C, which is not that different from modern summer temperatures in the same place. Either I am interpreting the seasonal bias of my proxy incorrectly &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/project/soil_carbonates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(see other projects)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;  the subtropics were surprisingly cool. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018PA003391&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this project is to determine if greenhouse climates were seasonally equable or not. To answer this, I helped my colleague Landon Burgener in his efforts to compare temperature estimates from a myriad of proxies that likely record different seasonal temperatures. We looked at Cretaceous paleosol deposits in Utah and Montana. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.palaeo.2018.12.004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Utah.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
