<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Goldschmidt 2020 - Virtual presentation</title>
      <link>/project/goldschmidt_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/goldschmidt_2020/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style = &#34;color:royalblue&#34;&gt;
&lt;font size = &#34;6&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://goldschmidt.info/2020/abstracts/abstractView?id=2020003403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fingerprinting Soil Water Evaporation with Triple Oxygen Isotopes of Pedogenic Carbonates&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style = &#34;color:gray&#34;&gt;
 &lt;font size=&#34;4&#34;&gt;Julia Kelson, Tyler Huth, Naomi Levin, and Ben Passey
Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor MI &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style = &#34;color:gray&#34;&gt;
Session 14d: Geochemical indicators of paste climate and environmental change
Chat @ Monday June 22, 20:06-20:09 (EDT)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/a&gt;     |     &lt;a href=&#34;#results&#34;&gt;Triple Oxygen Isotope Results&lt;/a&gt;     |     &lt;a href=&#34;#model&#34;&gt;Bonus modeling&lt;/a&gt;
|    &lt;a href=&#34;#conclusions&#34;&gt;Implications for Paleo &amp;amp; Future work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;intro&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation:&lt;/strong&gt; Soil (pedogenic) carbonates are an important archive of terrestrial paleoclimate. In particular, their oxygen isotope composition ($\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O) is used to reconstruct the $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of ancient meteoric waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem:&lt;/strong&gt; To what extent is the $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil water (and resulting soil carbonate) modified by evaporation? If soil carbonates form during evaporative dewatering, it is likely that their parent water $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O is modified by evaporation. If unrecognized, this could lead to erroneously high estimates of $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of ancient precipitation.  On the other hand, if soil carbonates form as a result of rootwater uptake and/or respiration-induced changes in soil CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, the parent water $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O might be a faithful recorder of $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of meteoric waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What we are doing:&lt;/strong&gt; We are measuring the triple oxygen isotope composition of modern soil carbonates from various environments. Evaporation will cause a deviation from the expected relationship between $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O and $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O in water and resulting carbonate (&lt;a href=&#34;#Figure1&#34;&gt;Figure 1&lt;/a&gt;) (Landais et al., 2006; Luz and Barkan, 2010; Passey et al., 2014; Gázquez et al., 2018; Surma et al., 2018; Passey and Levin, in review). Thus the ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O composition of soil carbonates should indicate the extent to which their parent soil waters were evaporated (&lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/primer/tripleoprimer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Primer on Triple Oxygen Isotopes here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;Figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/17O_excess4.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Figure 1:** Schematic of relationship between  $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;18&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O and  $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O (left panel) and $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;18&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O and ∆&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O (right panel). ∆&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O is insensitive to the $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;18&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O of the carbonate parent water. Evaporated waters will have low ∆&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O values relative to their parent waters.&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Schematic of relationship between  $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O and  $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O (left panel) and $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O and ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O (right panel). ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O is insensitive to the $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of the carbonate parent water. Evaporated waters will have low ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O values relative to their parent waters.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-name-results-a-triple-oxygen-isotope-results&#34;&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;results&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Triple Oxygen Isotope Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preliminary results:&lt;/strong&gt; Soil carbonate ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O ranges from approximately -170 to -110 per meg, which corresponds with parent waters that range from -35 to + 25 per meg (&lt;a href=&#34;#Methods&#34;&gt;Methods below&lt;/a&gt;) (&lt;a href=&#34;#Figure2&#34;&gt;Figure 2&lt;/a&gt;). These values are generally lower than unevaporated meteoric waters (i.e., rain and rivers), and at the lowest, resemble evaporated meteoric waters (i.e., closed basin lakes). Thus far, a complicated relationship between aridity and ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil carbonates is emerging. We speculate that there might be the hint of some kind of “threshold aridity.” Below such a threshold aridity (more arid) we observe a spread in ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O. Above such a threshold (less arid) we observe relatively high ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O  values of soil waters (less evaporation).  This pattern might indicate that soil carbonates form during evaporation in the most arid environments (AI&amp;lt; 0.2). In semi-arid to humid environments (AI &amp;gt; 0.2), soil carbonate forms via other processes and/or soil waters are regularly recharged with non-evaporated waters. In such an environment, $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil carbonates might be more reliable recorders of rainfall $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;Figure2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/WaterCompilation_inskcapeedited.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Figure 2:** Reconstructed soil water ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O (black dots) and ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O of meteoric waters (Aron et al., Chem Geo, in prep) (colored dots). Reconstructed soil water ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O values are low compared to most meteoric waters; we interpret this pattern as indicating that many soil waters overprinted by some amount of evaporation.&#34; width=&#34;700&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Reconstructed soil water ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O (black dots) and ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of meteoric waters (Aron et al., Chem Geo, in prep) (colored dots). Reconstructed soil water ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O values are low compared to most meteoric waters; we interpret this pattern as indicating that many soil waters overprinted by some amount of evaporation.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;Figure3&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/AIplot_inkscapeedited.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Figure 3:** Calculated ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O of soil waters reconstructed from soil carbonates. Aridity index is calculated as the mean annual precipitation (MAP) divided by potential evapotranspiration (PET) using WorldClim data (Beverly et al., in prep; Fick and Hijmans 2017). The black outline indicates data that is newly presented in this work (measurements made at the University of Michigan). The data from Texas, USA are from Ji (2016); all other data are from Passey et al. (2014). &#34; width=&#34;700&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3:&lt;/strong&gt; Calculated ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil waters reconstructed from soil carbonates. Aridity index is calculated as the mean annual precipitation (MAP) divided by potential evapotranspiration (PET) using WorldClim data (Beverly et al., in prep; Fick and Hijmans 2017). The black outline indicates data that is newly presented in this work (measurements made at the University of Michigan). The data from Texas, USA are from Ji (2016); all other data are from Passey et al. (2014).
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-modeling-of-triple-oxygen-isotopes-in-a-soil-profile&#34;&gt;Bonus: Modeling of Triple Oxygen Isotopes in a Soil Profile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaporation only&lt;/strong&gt;: We’ve started to model ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O in a soil profile using the TOUGHREACT numerical simulation program. Below, we have plotted monthly time steps for a 1-D soil profile undergoing one year of evaporation (&lt;a href=&#34;#Figure4&#34;&gt;Figure 4&lt;/a&gt;). The model is isothermal, atmospheric relative humidity is set to 40 %, and the model does not incorporate transpiration. The year of evaporation results in an enormous ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-soil water excursion – up to -100 per meg lower than starting ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O (0 per meg) [see also the similar theoretical profile of Barnes and Allison (1983)]. Because a year of uninterrupted evaporation would only occur in the driest locations on earth (e.g., the non-vegetated Atacama Desert), this scenario shows the maximum potential effect of evaporation on ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-soil water and therefore ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-soil carbonate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;Figure4&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/evapOnly_1yr.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Figure 4:** Modeling D’17O of a soil profile. One year of evaporation (isothermal soil profile). &#34; width=&#34;700&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4:&lt;/strong&gt; Modeling D’17O of a soil profile. One year of evaporation (isothermal soil profile).
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A little more realistic:&lt;/strong&gt; To give a sense of the range of ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-soil water in a more realistic scenario, we modeled the Adam’s Ranch Soil Climate Analysis Network site in central New Mexico, a semi-arid environment (mean annual precipitation of 230 mm/yr) where soil carbonate readily forms. As above, we modeled an isothermal, non-vegetated system (soil temperature = 15 °C, atmospheric relative humidity = 44 %). &lt;a href=&#34;#Figure5&#34;&gt;Figure 5&lt;/a&gt; below shows the evolution of soil water ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O after the largest rain event on record (initial value of +35 per meg) from 2011–2015, ending just before the next rain event (Figure 5). The results suggest that ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O excursions of up to 20-25 per meg are possible from evaporation alone, although after most rain events ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-soil water only changes by 10-15 per meg before the next infiltration event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;Figure5&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/AdamsRanch_day984_1019_v2.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Figure 5:** Time steps of ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O-soil water after the September 10, 2013 rain event at Adam’s Ranch, New Mexico. The ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O of soil water resets to the rainfall value (&amp;#43;35 per meg) after a storm, then evolves to lower ∆’&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O with drying; the plot stops at 35 days, just before the next rain event. Soil profile is held at 15 °C, atmosphere at 12.5 °C. &#34; width=&#34;800&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5:&lt;/strong&gt; Time steps of ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-soil water after the September 10, 2013 rain event at Adam’s Ranch, New Mexico. The ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil water resets to the rainfall value (+35 per meg) after a storm, then evolves to lower ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O with drying; the plot stops at 35 days, just before the next rain event. Soil profile is held at 15 °C, atmosphere at 12.5 °C.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implications for paleoclimate reconstructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil carbonates can identify if parent soil waters have been evaporated. This will help workers evaluate the fidelity of their record for reconstructing $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O  of meteoric waters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O promises to shed light on soil carbonate formation processes, with implications on how to interpret other stable isotope data from this widely used material&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preliminary data suggests that ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil carbonates relates to local aridity. More data will be required to establish this measurement as a true proxy for aridity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future work:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firstly, we need to finish the replicate analyses that were aborted when the University of Michigan shut down to slow the spread of Sars-Cov-2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re also interested in &lt;a href=&#34;#samples&#34;&gt;adding&lt;/a&gt; to our soil carbonate collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We plan to explore other environmental factors (i.e., external constraints on timing of carbonate formation, seasonality of precipitation, vegetation type, etc.) that might also explain the ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O variation that we observe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observations of local meteoric water ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O would give context to our reconstructed soil water values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are just starting numerical modeling of ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil waters (link to bonus figures below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Future, future work: measurements of ∆&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil water made through a seasonal cycle would be very useful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;samples&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Do you have samples to contribute?&lt;/strong&gt; We are still expanding our collection of soil carbonate samples to include in this study. We are most interested in soil carbonate samples that already have some kind of environmental or isotope context (i.e., stable and/or clumped isotope data, water isotope data, vegetation information, etc.). If you have samples from anywhere in the world that you’d like to share with us, please get in touch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;
This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Award No. 1854873 to JRK.
We&amp;rsquo;d like to thank Greg Hoke, Alexis Licht and Paolo Ballato for providing soil carbonate samples from Argentina, Myanmar, and Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name = &#34;Methods&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stable-isotope-methods&#34;&gt;Stable isotope methods:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Triple oxygen isotope measurements are being made at the IsoPaleoLab at the University of Michigan. We are using the acid digestion/reduction/fluorination method described in Passey et al. (2014). Multiple analyses of VSMOW2 and SLAP2 are performed during each analytical session and form the basis for normalization to the VSMOW-SLAP reference frame (Schoenemann et al., 2013).  International carbonate standards (NBS-18, NBS-19, IAEA 603) are analyzed along with unknowns, and an internal carbonate standard (102-GC-AZ01) is used to correct for systematic drift in ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O that is observed in some analytical sessions. The data shown in this presentation were analyzed in two analytical sessions (as established by CoF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; reactors number 13 and 14 at IPL). These sessions spanned from December 2019 to March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Where shown, ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil waters is reconstructed from the soil carbonates using the ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of soil carbonate, an estimate of growth temperature from clumped isotopes (∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;) and a combined mineral-water and acid fractionation factor of $\theta$&lt;sub&gt;a-c-w&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5242 (Passey et al., 2014). The &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;$\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;c-w&lt;/sub&gt; is calculated using the equation from Kim and O&amp;rsquo;Neil (1997) and multiplied by an acid fractionation factor of 1.0081 for acid digestion of calcite at 90 °C (Kim et al., 2007):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;$\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;c-w&lt;/sub&gt; = 1.0081*$e^{((18030/(T)-32.42)/1000)}$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$\theta$&lt;sub&gt;a-c-w&lt;/sub&gt;  = ln(&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; $\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;c-w&lt;/sub&gt;)/ln(&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; $\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;c-w&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where T is carbonate growth temperature in Kelvin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Error bars in ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O are 1 standard error, which is calculated by dividing the standard deviation of 0.018 (long-term SD of an internal carbonate standard, 102-GC-AZ01) by the square root of the number of replicate analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aron, P.G., Levin, N.E., Beverly, E.J., Huth, T.E., Passey, B.H., Pelletier, E.M., Poulsen, C.J., Winkelstern, I.Z., Yarian, D.A. (in prep). Global variations of triple oxygen isotopes in meteoric waters. Chemical Geology, to be submitted by June 30, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barnes C. J., and Allison G. B. (1983). The distribution of Deuterium and 18O in dry soils: 1. Theory. Journal of Hydrology, 60, 141–156.
Fick, S. E., and Hijmans, R. J. (2017). WorldClim 2: new 1-km spatial resolution climate surfaces for global land areas. Int. J. of Climatol. 37, 4302–4315.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gázquez, F., Evans, N. P., Herwartz, D., Bauska, T. K., Morellon, M., Surma, J., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Hodell, D. A. (2016, December). Triple Oxygen and Deuterium Isotopes in Gypsum Hydration Water for Quantitative Paleo-humidity Reconstructions. In AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ji, H. (2016). Triple oxygen isotopes in lake waters, lacustrine carbonates and soil carbonates: An indicator for evaporation (Doctoral dissertation, Johns Hopkins University).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kim, S. T., &amp;amp; O&amp;rsquo;Neil, J. R. (1997). Equilibrium and nonequilibrium oxygen isotope effects in synthetic carbonates. Geochimica et cosmochimica acta, 61(16), 3461-3475.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kim, S. T., Mucci, A., &amp;amp; Taylor, B. E. (2007). Phosphoric acid fractionation factors for calcite and aragonite between 25 and 75 C: revisited. Chemical Geology, 246(3-4), 135-146.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Landais, A., Barkan, E., Yakir, D., &amp;amp; Luz, B. (2006). The triple isotopic composition of oxygen in leaf water. Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 70(16), 4105-4115.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luz, B., &amp;amp; Barkan, E. (2010). Variations of 17O/16O and 18O/16O in meteoric waters. Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 74(22), 6276-6286.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passey, B. H., Hu, H., Ji, H., Montanari, S., Li, S., Henkes, G. A., &amp;amp; Levin, N. E. (2014). Triple oxygen isotopes in biogenic and sedimentary carbonates. Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 141, 1-25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passey, B.H.  and Levin, N.E. (in review) Triple oxygen isotgopes in carbonates, biological apatites, and continental paleoclimate reconstruction.  Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenemann, S. W., Schauer, A. J., &amp;amp; Steig, E. J. (2013). Measurement of SLAP2 and GISP δ17O and proposed VSMOW‐SLAP normalization for δ17O and 17Oexcess. Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry, 27(5), 582-590.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Triple Oxygen Isotopes</title>
      <link>/primer/tripleoprimer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/primer/tripleoprimer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style = &#34;color:gray&#34;&gt;
A dummie&amp;rsquo;s guide to triple oxygen isotopes in carbonate.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxygen has one major isotope, &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O, and two minor isotopes, &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O and &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O. A measurement of the abundance of &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O is widely used in geochemistry ($\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O) as a tracer for hydrologic processes.  It was long assumed that stuyding &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O would not yield additional useful information because the fractionation would be about half that of &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O, following a relationship that is predicted by mass-dependent (equilibrium) fractionation ($\theta$ = 0.529 for equilibrium fractionation, Luz and Barkan 2010):&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/TripleOprimer/path235.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1: Predicted relationship between $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;18&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O and $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O given equilibrium fractionation. $\theta$&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;a-b&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;  = ln(&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17/16&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; $\alpha$&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;a-b&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;)/ln(&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;18/16&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; $\alpha$&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;a-b&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;), where $\alpha$&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;a-b&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; is the fractionation factor between two phases (like calcite-water). &#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 1: Predicted relationship between $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O and $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O given equilibrium fractionation. $\theta$&lt;sub&gt;a-b&lt;/sub&gt;  = ln(&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; $\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;a-b&lt;/sub&gt;)/ln(&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; $\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;a-b&lt;/sub&gt;), where $\alpha$&lt;sub&gt;a-b&lt;/sub&gt; is the fractionation factor between two phases (like calcite-water).
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that the axes of Figure 1 use “delta-prime” notation, a slight variation on the more familiar delta notation. This notation is used to remove the slight curvature in the relationship between $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O and $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O (Miller, 2002):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$\delta$’x = ln($\delta$x+1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$\delta$&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O can deviate from this relationship if non-equilibrium fractionation occurs (i.e., $\theta$ ≠ 0.529).  Evaporation is an example of one such  fractionation process that carries $\theta$ = 0.5185 (Barkan and Luz, 2007). Yes, 0.5185 might seem about the same as .529, but with sufficiently high precision instruments this deviation can be measured. This deviation from the expected relationship between $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O and $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O is called ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O, (analogous to the familiar d-excess), and is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$\Delta$’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O = $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O – $\lambda$ * $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/TripleOprimer/path236.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 2: Schematic of $\Delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 2: Schematic of $\Delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that I&amp;rsquo;ve used $\lambda$ = 0.528, which is the empirically observed relationship in meteoric waters (Luz and Barkan 2010). The $\lambda$ notation expresses that it is an empirical relationship that may combine a number of different fractionations, as opposed to the $\theta$ used above that describes a single, well-defined fractionation (like the equilibrium fractionation, diffusion, or acid fractionation). ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O is expressed in permille (with values that ranges from +0.10 to -0.2), or in per meg (with values that range from +100 to -200).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, $\Delta$’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O can be used to identify evaporation of parent waters and carbonate minerals. Measuring $\Delta$’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O promises to be useful in terrestrial hydroclimate where d18O alone can be ambiguous.  Let’s consider the water bottle of Seattle tap water ($\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O = -10 ‰) that I accidentally brought with me when I moved to in Michigan last fall.  If I let this water bottle sit with a lid off, it would evaporate and eventually reach a $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O= -6 ‰.  At that point, it would be impossible to distinguish my imported Seattle water from that of local Ann Arbor tap water using $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O analyses. $\Delta$’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O could be used to readily identify which water was evaporated; the Seattle water would have a $\Delta$’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O value that is about 0.10 ‰ lower than that of the Michigan water (evaporation experiments in Li et al., 2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$\Delta$’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O has the potential to be useful in addition to the more familiar d-excess for two reasons. The first is the fractionation in oxygen isotopes is not very sensitive to temperature (i.e., Angert et al., 2004). The second is that carbonate minerals are widely preserved in the geologic record, where it is difficult to find co-occurring preservation of hydrogen and oxygen that would be necessary to calculate d-excess. Furthermore, the growth temperature can be directly measured from the same carbonate mineral (using clumps), allowing for a simultaneous estimate of environmental temperature and hydrologic processes.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/TripleOprimer/rect7101.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 3: Schematic of $\Delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;17&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O vs $\delta$&amp;#39;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;18&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;O in waters&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 3: Schematic of $\Delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O vs $\delta$&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O in waters
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In studies of paleo-hydroclimate, we could use ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O to parse out if changes in $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O were due to Rayleigh distillation (i.e., rainout over a mountain range) or due to evaporation. Other processes that cause kinetic fractionation could also be investigated (i.e., speleothems, as predicted in Guo and Zhou, 2019).  Note that ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O should be independent of the starting $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O composition. It might even be possible to use the ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O of carbonates to reconstruct the $\delta$&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O of primary meteoric waters (i.e., lake carbonates in Passey and Ji, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring ∆’&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O in carbonate materials posed a technical challenge to isotope geochemists. Usually the isotopic composition of a carbonate mineral is determined by first digesting the CaCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in phosphoric acid, then measuring the isotope abundances in the evolved CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas. However, &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C-&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O-&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O interferes with the measurement of &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C-&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O-&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O. So, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas evolved from solid  CaCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; needs to be converted to O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; for measurement. Passey et al. (2014) describe the acid digestion, reduction, and fluorination method which is currently in place at the University of Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A proxy for all seasons? A synthesis of clumped isotope data from Holocene soil carbonates </title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper highlighted in Elsevier Special Issue for International Women&#39;s Day</title>
      <link>/post/womensdayhighlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/womensdayhighlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My clumped isotope calibration paper (Kelson et al., 2017) has been chosen to be included in a special issue for International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day 2020. From Elsevier: &amp;ldquo;To mark International Women’s Day 2020, we are proud to promote a selection of recent and highly cited articles from lead female authors, who have published in top Elsevier Earth and Planetary Science journals.  These articles are free to view for 6 months.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/physical-sciences-and-engineering/earth-and-planetary-sciences/journals/international-womens-day?utm_campaign=STMJ_108700_SISSUE&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_dgroup=108700_MAIN_NOAB_SGL_ALL&amp;amp;utm_acid=180503095&amp;amp;SIS_ID=1148&amp;amp;dgcid=STMJ_108700_SISSUE&amp;amp;CMX_ID=ECR-1148&amp;amp;utm_in=DM657477&amp;amp;utm_source=AC_30&amp;amp;utm_term=108700_SISSUE_MAIN_NOAB_SINGLE_ALL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Access the special issue with this link.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Started NSF-EAR postdoc in Ann Arbor, MI</title>
      <link>/post/arrived_mi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/arrived_mi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I arrived in MI and joined Sierra Petersen&amp;rsquo;s SCIPP (Stable and Clumped Isotopes for Paleoclimate &amp;amp; Paleoceanography) group. With two postdocs, 5 graduate students, and 3 undergrads, the lab feels like an active and exciting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, I&amp;rsquo;ll be working on Sierra&amp;rsquo;s new Nu instrument. The Nu allows for smaller sample sizes for clumped isotope analyses. Hopefully this will allow me to micro-sample shell and resolve seasonal variations in temperature. Also I&amp;rsquo;ll be working with IsoPaleoLab (Levin/Passey lab) to measure triple oxygen isotopes in carbonates with the goal of quantifying aridity in greenhouse climates.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SCIPP_group.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Portrait of the SCIPPers in Sierra&amp;#39;s backyard&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Portrait of the SCIPPers in Sierra&amp;rsquo;s backyard
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, former labmate Mike T took me to the Big House to see my first college football game. The UM school spirit is truly exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/BigHouse.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I think Michigan won?&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    I think Michigan won?
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer travels</title>
      <link>/post/summer_travels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/summer_travels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maybe most academics don&amp;rsquo;t take long vacations, but I am taking this summer off! The flexibility in postdoc-start-date allowed me to take a break after graduating from UW in June. So, what am I doing with my time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will mostly be in Copenhagen, Denmark, exploring Scandinavian craft beer, swimming in the canals, going for bike rides, and finishing manuscripts from my PhD work. I also plan to travel to Italy, Norway, Czechia, and Sweden. Then I&amp;rsquo;ll head back to North America for a backpacking trip in the Sierra and a sea kayaking trip in British Columbia before driving eastward to my new basecamp in Ann Arbor.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Steno.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Did you know Steno was Danish?&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Did you know Steno was Danish?
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/bikes_CPH.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Endless bikes at the bike rack in central station, CPH.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Endless bikes at the bike rack in central station, CPH.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Tuborg_CPH.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Not quite a craft beer...&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Not quite a craft beer&amp;hellip;
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Graduate Student Perspective: Graduation Speech</title>
      <link>/talk/graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/graduation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at UW Earth &amp; Space Science Graduation</title>
      <link>/post/uw_ess_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/uw_ess_graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;UW Earth and Space Sciences graduation really started off right - with a fire alarm! The alarm went off just when the chair, Ken Creager, was trying to get the ceremony started. Everyone evacuated, waited for the fire department to ascertain that there was not actually a fire, then we re-started the ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/doorway_grad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Goofing around with Mike Turzewski (fellow grad) and  Kate Huntington (my advisor). &#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Goofing around with Mike Turzewski (fellow grad) and  Kate Huntington (my advisor).
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, I was honored to give the graduation speech.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/speaking_at_grad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Best outfit to give a talk in ever.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Best outfit to give a talk in ever.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Improved 17O Correction on Interlaboratory Agreement in Clumped Isotope Calibrations, Estimates of Mineral‐Specific Offsets, and Temperature Dependence of Acid Digestion Fractionation</title>
      <link>/publication/petersen_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/petersen_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nicole Sarieddine presents at Undergrad Research Symposium</title>
      <link>/post/nicole_mgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nicole_mgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nicole culminated her 2 years of undergraduate research with a presentation at the UW Undergraduate Research Symposium. She worked on a slough of projects relating to the climate reconstructions using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates. At this symposium, she presented results on using remotely-sensed soil moisture data to predict when soil carbonates form in North America. The jury is still out on whether or not remotely sensed soil moisture data is actually useful for this application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the equable climate problem during the Late Cretaceous greenhouse using paleosol carbonate clumped isotope temperatures from the Campanian of the Western Interior Basin, USA</title>
      <link>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warm Terrestrial Subtropics During the Paleocene and Eocene: Carbonate Clumped Isotope (Δ47) Evidence From the Tornillo Basin, Texas (USA)</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbonate Clumped Isotopes: Certainties and Uncertainties of Thermometry and Eocene Subtropical Paleoclimate</title>
      <link>/talk/wce_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/wce_seminar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern soil carbonates</title>
      <link>/project/soil_carbonates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/soil_carbonates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am researching how and when soil carbonates form. This research is necessary in order to use ancient soil carbonates for paleoclimate reconstructions. This research also helps understand how and where inorganic carbon is stored, which has implications for understanding the global carbon cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly assumed that soil carbonates form in the warm season. This assumption is reasonable because the warm season is when plants are growing (and evapo-transpirating), the sun is shining, and the soil is drying out. All of those physical processes should promote supersaturation with respect to calcite.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm.png&#34; alt=&#34;Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, soil carbonates can form in the winter, spring, summer, or fall as well. Environmental factors that control this timing include plant activity, persistent snowpack, soil texture, heavy summer rain, etc.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am using a couple of different approaches to determine when soil carbonates form and how to interpret their isotopic composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106259&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;This paper reviews clumped isotope data on soil carbonates. &lt;/a&gt; The take home: soil carbonate formation temperatures are all over the place! A warm-season bias is the most common, but formation temperatures deviate widely from mean annual air temperatures. We aren&amp;rsquo;t able to explain this variation in formation temperatures easily with environmental data and existing hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I am using a numerical model called HYDRUS-1D to predict the timing of carbonate formation. This work will allow us to delve into individual processes that are impossible to disentangle with empirical data.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HYDRUS.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mentoring</title>
      <link>/outreach/mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/outreach/mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have mentored several undergraduate students at the University of Washington. It is helpful to have an army of people when trying to grow synthetic calcite!&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/Shana.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Undergraduate Shana filtering calcite, June 2019&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Undergraduate Shana filtering calcite, June 2019
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of watching Nicole graduate with her BS in Earth &amp;amp; Space Sciences - the same day that I walked for my PhD.






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/graduation_nicole.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kate Huntington, Nicole Sarieddine and me in front of Johnson Hall on graduation day June 2019&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Kate Huntington, Nicole Sarieddine and me in front of Johnson Hall on graduation day June 2019
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently recruiting an undergraduate student to work on Paleocene shells from the East Coast. I&amp;rsquo;m looking for someone who wants to get their hands on samples - doing drilling and milling, potentially for annual resolution seasonality if the samples cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/IMG_0721.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Look at this excellent shell preservation from the Aquia Fm, just waiting for an eager UM student.&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Look at this excellent shell preservation from the Aquia Fm, just waiting for an eager UM student.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sediment Fingerprinting</title>
      <link>/project/sed_fingerprinting_or/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sed_fingerprinting_or/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am interested in applying my geochemistry skills to problems in sediment transport and landscape evolution on human timescales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, took advantage of an NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program offshoot called GRIP (Graduate Research Internship Program) (alphabet soup) to spend about three months working at the USGS Water Science Center in Portland, Oregon. My task was to figure out if it would be possible to use the chemical composition, or &amp;lsquo;fingerprint,&amp;rsquo; of sediment to trace where in a watershed the phosphorous-rich sediment comes from.  The river of interest, the Sprague River, has a long, complicated history of conflict between ranchers, native populations, and environmental regulators.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Sprague/trampled.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Banks trampled by cows and fencing across the river. Not difficult to imagine an unnatural source of sediment here.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Banks trampled by cows and fencing across the river. Not difficult to imagine an unnatural source of sediment here.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbonate Clumped isotopes</title>
      <link>/primer/clumpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/primer/clumpy/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CO2molecule.png&#34; alt=&#34;a clumpy CO&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; molecule&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    a clumpy CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The term ‘clumped isotopes’ refers to the co-existence of two rare, heavy isotopes in a single molecule, or - get ready for a mouthful – a ‘doubly substituted isotopologue’. In the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule above, there are heavy isotopes (&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O and &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) bonded together. (FYI, their common/light counterparts are &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C and &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O). This makes for a molecule with an atomic mass of 47, hence the common ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; notation for &amp;lsquo;clumped isotopes&amp;rsquo;. Conveniently for paleoclimatologist, the rare/heavy isotopes preferentially clump at lower temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/TD47cartoon.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But how does this work? Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine a balloon full of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas with a fixed number of light and heavy isotopes each. In a balloon held at 1000 °C, the system is chaotic. Bonds are vibrating and wiggling and nothing really settles down. In this high-temperature system, the heavy and light isotopes end up being randomly distributed amongst the molecules.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/hotballoon.png&#34; alt=&#34;Only one clumpy molecule in the hot balloon. Heavy isotopes are dark colors, light isotopes are light colors.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Only one clumpy molecule in the hot balloon. Heavy isotopes are dark colors, light isotopes are light colors.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a balloon held at lower temperatures (&amp;lt;1000 °C), the system can reach a more energetically favorable state. Clumping heavy isotopes together is favorable because it slightly reduces the vibrational energy and increases bond strength. So more clumps will occur at lower temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/coldballoon.png&#34; alt=&#34;Three clumpy molecules in the cold balloon. Note same number of heavy isotopes.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Three clumpy molecules in the cold balloon. Note same number of heavy isotopes.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thus, clumped isotope geochemistry is not concerned with the total number of heavy isotopes in a system, but rather how those heavy isotopes are arranged within the molecules. We do need to know the number of heavy isotopes in the system, though, so we can calculate how many clumps we would expect if they were randomly arranged vs. how many we actually have measured. Then, we can estimate the temperature at which that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule formed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, what is measured is the clumpiness of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas that we get by digesting a carbonate mineral in acid. Common targets are soil carbonates and shells. With a little bit more work (see other projects), we can use the clumpiness we measure to estimate temperatures at or near the surface of the Earth millions of years ago. This thermometer is not based on biology nor does it depend on the isotopic composition of the water from which the mineral grew. That makes for a powerful, quantitative thermometer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing the Methods of Clumped Isotope Geochemistry</title>
      <link>/project/clumpy_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/clumpy_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first measurements of ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas evolved from carbonates were published in 2006 by Ghosh et al. While that was over a decade ago, the small size of the ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; signal has ensured that precise and accurate measurements are a challenge. Development and refinement of the method is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/source_cleaning.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Very carefully putting the source back into the MAT 253&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Very carefully putting the source back into the MAT 253
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I jumped into the field in 2014, the biggest challenge was disagreement amongst empirical calibrations of the ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;-temperature relationship. I designed a series of calcite precipitation experiments to address the cause of the discrepancy amongst previously published calibrations. I thought this would be a small side project but it turned into a chapter of my PhD dissertation and a paper in GCA: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these calcite precipitation experiments, myself and others at UW Isolab discovered that the choice of &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O correction parameters was introducing errors into the calculation of ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;. These &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O correction parameters are required to calculate ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; when measured with mass spectrometry (i.e., in all labs making clumped isotope measurements). As a result of this effort, all clumped labs are now using a set of correction parameters recommended by IUPAC (presented in Brand et al., 2010), rather than the parameters from Santrock et al. (1985) that IsoDat (mass spec software) defaulted to. This work resulted in a paper in RCMS:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&lt;/a&gt;. It also provided the motivation for a large, multi-laboratory effort to recalculate previous ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;-temperature empirical calibrations, spearheaded by Sierra Petersen: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These efforts have significantly improved our confidence in the temperatures we estimate from unknown samples. However, methods can always be improved - good isotope geochemistry requires constant vigilance!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outreach</title>
      <link>/outreach/isolab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/outreach/isolab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Presenting geoscience research to K-12 students is a great way to provide science opportunities to underserved communities and demonstrate the possibility for careers in STEM. Plus, it is usually pretty fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I helped organize field trips for hundreds of students to visit University of Washington&amp;rsquo;s IsoLab throughout several years.  This included a recurring field trip from a high school in South Seattle.






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/IsoLab_Outreach_Jan2015.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Giving a lab tour to Pacific Lutheran University students.&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Giving a lab tour to Pacific Lutheran University students.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through UW Rockin&amp;rsquo; Out, a graduate-student-run volunteer organization, I have also shared my science in elementary school classrooms, participated in science nights, and organized outdoor field trip opportunities for local schools.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/AGU2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Explaining my AGU poster to 30 high school students AND my high school chemistry teacher (what a kick!)&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Explaining my AGU poster to 30 high school students AND my high school chemistry teacher (what a kick!)
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward a universal carbonate clumped isotope calibration: Diverse synthesis and preparatory methods suggest a single temperature relationship</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choice of 17O correction affects clumped isotope (∆47) values of CO2 measured with mass spectrometry</title>
      <link>/publication/schauer_etal_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schauer_etal_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenhouse climates of the Cenozoic</title>
      <link>/project/greenhouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenhouse/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Globe.png&#34; alt=&#34;Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The late Cretaceous though the early Eocene is an intriguing period of Earth history because of the geologic evidence for globally warm climates that corresponds with high concentrations of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere. Studying these high CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates can  potentially illuminate what high-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates will be like in the future. However, a couple of basic questions about these so-called greenhouse climate regimes drive the paleoclimate research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first, seemingly simple, question is: how hot was it really? One way to quantify earth surface temperatures is by using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates that formed during that time period. I used a seres of stacked paleosols from Big Bend National Park, Texas, USA to estimate air temperatures in the subtropics (30 °N).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SamplingBigYellow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My temperature estimates were intriguingly cold - I estimate summer temperatures of 32 °C, which is not that different from modern summer temperatures in the same place. Either I am interpreting the seasonal bias of my proxy incorrectly &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/project/soil_carbonates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(see other projects)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;   the subtropics were surprisingly cool. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018PA003391&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this project is to determine if greenhouse climates were seasonally equable or not. To answer this, I helped my colleague Landon Burgener in his efforts to compare temperature estimates from a myriad of proxies that likely record different seasonal temperatures. We looked at Cretaceous paleosol deposits in Utah and Montana. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.palaeo.2018.12.004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Utah.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m actively working on a late Paleocene to early Eocene record from the Goler Formation in California. This is another near coastal section that fortunately has a variety of carbonates to work with - including oyster shells.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hobbies</title>
      <link>/project/personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/personal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I try to balance work with some life&amp;hellip; Here&amp;rsquo;s a smattering of what I get up to.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/Trudging_up_Muir_PC_SeanLahusen.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Skinning on Mt Rainier, with Mt. Adams chillin in the background. PC Sean Lahusen&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Skinning on Mt Rainier, with Mt. Adams chillin in the background. PC Sean Lahusen
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/canoe.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Building a skin-on-frame canoe. The boat kind of looks like it would float in this picture.&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Building a skin-on-frame canoe. The boat kind of looks like it would float in this picture.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/Are_we_in_theBC_GlacierPeakW.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Have we reached the backcountry yet? Glacier Peak Wilderness, WA. PC Todd Anderson&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Have we reached the backcountry yet? Glacier Peak Wilderness, WA. PC Todd Anderson
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/IMG_9330.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I&amp;#39;m usually happiest when I&amp;#39;m in glaciated landscapes, but that is not really a feasible place to live. Here I&amp;#39;m goofing off with my sister Suzanne in Norway.&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    I&amp;rsquo;m usually happiest when I&amp;rsquo;m in glaciated landscapes, but that is not really a feasible place to live. Here I&amp;rsquo;m goofing off with my sister Suzanne in Norway.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/Skiing_InspirationGlacier.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Learning how to ski with a heavy pack on the Inspiration Glacier, North Cascades, WA. PC David Lilien&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Learning how to ski with a heavy pack on the Inspiration Glacier, North Cascades, WA. PC David Lilien
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/DeceptionPass_crop.png&#34; alt=&#34;Finishing the Deception Pass 50k, Anacortes, WA, December 2018&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Finishing the Deception Pass 50k, Anacortes, WA, December 2018
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
