<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mentoring on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/tags/mentoring/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mentoring on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/mentoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mentoring</title>
      <link>/outreach/mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/outreach/mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoy involving undergraduates in my field and laboratory research.  I have mentored several undergraduate students at the University of Washington and at the University of Michigan. Through my ongoing CZ17O project, I&amp;rsquo;ve recruited four students at UMich who are helping at various levels, including mapping geomorphology, sample preparation, and sample analysis on a mass spectrometer. We have one student at Boise State who is collecting soil samples on an ongoing basis in Idaho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With undergraduates Margaret, Miriam and Kirsten, and graduate student from IsoPaleoLab @ UMich, we took a all-hands-on-deck field trip to our local outcrop of soils in the Edwin S George Reserve near Hell, MI in September 2021.






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/ESGR_ugrads_lecture.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Believe it or not, there&amp;#39;s calcite in the soils in this forest.&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Believe it or not, there&amp;rsquo;s calcite in the soils in this forest.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of watching Nicole graduate with her BS in Earth &amp;amp; Space Sciences - the same day that I walked for my PhD.






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/graduation_nicole.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kate Huntington, Nicole Sarieddine and me in front of Johnson Hall on graduation day June 2019&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Kate Huntington, Nicole Sarieddine and me in front of Johnson Hall on graduation day June 2019
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to have an army of people when trying to grow synthetic calcite! Several undergraduates, including Shana, were instrumental to precipitating synthetic calcite as a part of my clumped isotope calibration paper.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outreach/Shana.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Undergraduate Shana filtering calcite, June 2019&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Undergraduate Shana filtering calcite, June 2019
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
