<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>clumped isotopes on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/tags/clumped-isotopes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in clumped isotopes on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/clumped-isotopes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Improved 17O Correction on Interlaboratory Agreement in Clumped Isotope Calibrations, Estimates of Mineral‐Specific Offsets, and Temperature Dependence of Acid Digestion Fractionation</title>
      <link>/publication/petersen_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/petersen_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the equable climate problem during the Late Cretaceous greenhouse using paleosol carbonate clumped isotope temperatures from the Campanian of the Western Interior Basin, USA</title>
      <link>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warm Terrestrial Subtropics During the Paleocene and Eocene: Carbonate Clumped Isotope (Δ47) Evidence From the Tornillo Basin, Texas (USA)</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbonate Clumped Isotopes: Certainties and Uncertainties of Thermometry and Eocene Subtropical Paleoclimate</title>
      <link>/talk/wce_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/wce_seminar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A primer</title>
      <link>/primer/clumpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/primer/clumpy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term ‘clumped isotopes’ refers to the co-existence of two rare heavy isotopes in a single molecule – or, get ready for a mouthful – a ‘doubly substituted isotopologue’.  We will consider the carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) molecule which is primarily made up of light carbon and oxygen isotopes (&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C and &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O) but will also have some of the rare heavy isotopes (&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C and &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O) (also &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O and others, ignore those for now). Imagine a ballon full of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas with a fixed number of light and heavy isotopes each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a ballon held at 1000 °C, the system is chaotic. Bonds are vibrating and wiggling and nothing really settles down. In this high-temperature system, the heavy and light isotopes end up being randomly distributed amongst the molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Image?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a ballon in lower temperatures, the system can reach a more energetically favorable state. Clumping heavy isotopes together is favorable because it slightly reduces the vibrational energy and increases bond strength. So more clumps will occur at lower temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Image?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, clumped isotope geochemistry is not concerned with the total number of heavy isotopes in a system, but rather how those heavy isotopes are arranged within the molecules. We do need to know the number of heavy isotopes in the system, though, so we can calculate how many clumps we would expect if they were randomly arranged vs. how many we actually have measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chemistry may seem boring but it is useful because it provides the basis of a geothermometer: if we measure the clumpiness of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas evolved from an ancient rock (carbonate mineral) then we can estimate the growth temperature of that mineral. And, with a little bit more work, we can use that to estimate temperatures at or near the surface of the Earth through millions of years. This thermometer is not based on biology nor does it depend on the isotopic composition of the water from which the mineral grew. Put together, that makes for a powerful, quantitative thermometer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing the Methods of Clumped Isotope Geochemistry</title>
      <link>/project/clumpy_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/clumpy_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first measurements of ∆47 of CO2 gas evolved from carbonates were published in 2006 by Ghosh et al. While that was over a decade ago, the small size of the ∆47 signal makes its measurement a technical challenge. Development and refinement of the method is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I jumped into the field in 2014, the biggest challenge was disagreement amongst empirical calibrations of the ∆47-temperature relationship. I designed a series of calcite precipitation experiments to address the cause of the discrepancy amongst previously published calibrations. I thought this would be a small side project but it turned into a chapter of my PhD dissertation and a paper in GCA: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these calcite precipitation experiments, myself and others at UW Isolab discovered that the choice of 17O correction parameters was introducing errors into the calculation of D47. These 17O correction parameters are required to calculate D47 when measured with mass spectrometry (i.e., in all labs making clumped isotope measurements). As a result of this effort, all clumped labs are now using a set of correction parameters recommended by IUPAC (presented in Brand et al., 2010), rather than the parameters from Santrock et al. (1985) that IsoDat (mass spec software) defaulted to. This work resulted in a paper in RCMS:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&lt;/a&gt;. It also provided the motivation for a large, multi-laboratory effort to recalculate previous ∆47-temperature empirical calibrations, spearheaded by Sierra Petersen: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These efforts have significantly improved our confidence in the temperatures we estimate from unknown samples. However, methods can always be improved - good isotope geochemistry requires constant vigilance!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward a universal carbonate clumped isotope calibration: Diverse synthesis and preparatory methods suggest a single temperature relationship</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choice of 17O correction affects clumped isotope (∆47) values of CO2 measured with mass spectrometry</title>
      <link>/publication/schauer_etal_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schauer_etal_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
