<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>clumped isotopes on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/tags/clumped-isotopes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in clumped isotopes on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/clumped-isotopes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking upstream with clumped and triple oxygen isotopes of estuarine oyster shells in the early Eocene of California, USA</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of pedogenic carbonate growth in the monsoonal tropical domain</title>
      <link>/publication/licht_etal_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/licht_etal_2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing isotopic estimates of paleoelevation from carbonates and volcanic glass from the Miocene-age Chucal Formation in northern Chile</title>
      <link>/publication/jimenez-rodriguez_etal_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/jimenez-rodriguez_etal_2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CZ17O: Triple Oxygen Isotopes in Soil Carbonates</title>
      <link>/project/cz17o/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cz17o/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Soils are key to understanding climate change in drylands given their importance in mediating the flux of both water and carbon. Pedogenic carbonates underly dryland soils and provide essential ground-level perspectives on climate change through geologic time and in the present. However, pedogenic carbonates currently fall short as tracers of water and carbon fluxes because we have an incomplete understanding of how they form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address the gap in our understanding of how soil carbonates form, my collaborator Naomi Levin and I are using triple oxygen isotope geochemistry (&lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/primer/tripleoprimer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;primer here&lt;/a&gt;) to directly assess the importance of evaporation during soil carbonate formation. We&amp;rsquo;re considering how and where biotic processes (root water uptake/transpiration) vs abiotic processes (evaporation) dominate soil carbonate formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working across aridity gradients in North America, specifically targeting two sites that are a part of the Drylands Critical Zone Network - Jornada, New Mexico, and Reynolds Creek, Idaho. Our driest soils sites are in the Mojave National Preserve which has an incredible network of above- and below- ground monitoring sites set up by our collaborator Ron Amundson (UC Berkeley).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/AImap_v3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Study sites take advantage of the natural gradient in aridity in the Western US.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Study sites take advantage of the natural gradient in aridity in the Western US.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is just the start of an NSF-funded two year project! So far, the project has been an awesome way to connect with collaborators who also love soils, isotopes, and drylands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preliminary data that provided the basis for our successful NSF proposal is described in my &lt;a href=&#34;(https://jrkelson.github.io/project/goldschmidt_2020/)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Goldschmidt presentation from 2020&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Bk_horizon_Reynolds.png&#34; alt=&#34;A beautiful calcic horizon exposed in an open trench at the Lower Sheep site in Reynolds Creek, Idaho.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    A beautiful calcic horizon exposed in an open trench at the Lower Sheep site in Reynolds Creek, Idaho.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>InterCarb: A Community Effort to Improve Interlaboratory Standardization of the Carbonate Clumped Isotope Thermometer Using Carbonate Standards</title>
      <link>/publication/bernasconi_etal_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bernasconi_etal_2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified clumped isotope thermometer calibration (0.5-1100 °C) using carbonate-based standardization</title>
      <link>/publication/anderson_etal_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/anderson_etal_2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A proxy for all seasons? A synthesis of clumped isotope data from Holocene soil carbonates </title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Improved 17O Correction on Interlaboratory Agreement in Clumped Isotope Calibrations, Estimates of Mineral‐Specific Offsets, and Temperature Dependence of Acid Digestion Fractionation</title>
      <link>/publication/petersen_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/petersen_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the equable climate problem during the Late Cretaceous greenhouse using paleosol carbonate clumped isotope temperatures from the Campanian of the Western Interior Basin, USA</title>
      <link>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/burgener_etal_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warm Terrestrial Subtropics During the Paleocene and Eocene: Carbonate Clumped Isotope (Δ47) Evidence From the Tornillo Basin, Texas (USA)</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbonate Clumped Isotopes: Certainties and Uncertainties of Thermometry and Eocene Subtropical Paleoclimate</title>
      <link>/talk/wce_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/wce_seminar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonality of soil carbonate formation</title>
      <link>/project/soil_carbonates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/soil_carbonates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When do soil carbonates form? We need to be able to answer this question in order to use ancient soil carbonates for paleoclimate reconstructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly assumed that soil carbonates form in the warm season. This assumption is reasonable because the warm season is when plants are growing (and evapo-transpirating), the sun is shining, and the soil is drying out. All of those physical processes should promote supersaturation with respect to calcite.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm.png&#34; alt=&#34;Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;BUT soil carbonates can form in the winter, spring, summer, or fall. Environmental factors that control this timing include plant activity, persistent snowpack, soil texture, heavy summer rain, etc.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am using multiple approaches to determine when soil carbonates form and how to interpret their isotopic composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106259&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;First, this paper reviews clumped isotope data on soil carbonates. &lt;/a&gt; Clumped isotope-based temperatures can reveal apparent seasonal biases in modern soil carbonates. The take home: soil carbonate formation temperatures are all over the place! A warm-season bias is the most common, but formation temperatures deviate widely from mean annual air temperatures. We aren&amp;rsquo;t able to explain this variation in formation temperatures easily with environmental data and existing hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I am using a numerical model called HYDRUS-1D to predict the timing of carbonate formation. This work will allow us to delve into individual processes that are impossible to disentangle with empirical data.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HYDRUS.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carbonate Clumped isotopes</title>
      <link>/primer/clumpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/primer/clumpy/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CO2molecule.png&#34; alt=&#34;a clumpy CO&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; molecule&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    a clumpy CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The term ‘clumped isotopes’ refers to the co-existence of two rare, heavy isotopes in a single molecule, or - get ready for a mouthful – a ‘doubly substituted isotopologue’. In the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule above, there are heavy isotopes (&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O and &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) bonded together. (FYI, their common/light counterparts are &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C and &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O). This makes for a molecule with an atomic mass of 47, hence the common ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; notation for &amp;lsquo;clumped isotopes&amp;rsquo;. Conveniently for paleoclimatologist, the rare/heavy isotopes preferentially clump at lower temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/TD47cartoon.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But how does this work? Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine a balloon full of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas with a fixed number of light and heavy isotopes each. In a balloon held at 1000 °C, the system is chaotic. Bonds are vibrating and wiggling and nothing really settles down. In this high-temperature system, the heavy and light isotopes end up being randomly distributed amongst the molecules.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/hotballoon.png&#34; alt=&#34;Only one clumpy molecule in the hot balloon. Heavy isotopes are dark colors, light isotopes are light colors.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Only one clumpy molecule in the hot balloon. Heavy isotopes are dark colors, light isotopes are light colors.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a balloon held at lower temperatures (&amp;lt;1000 °C), the system can reach a more energetically favorable state. Clumping heavy isotopes together is favorable because it slightly reduces the vibrational energy and increases bond strength. So more clumps will occur at lower temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/coldballoon.png&#34; alt=&#34;Three clumpy molecules in the cold balloon. Note same number of heavy isotopes.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Three clumpy molecules in the cold balloon. Note same number of heavy isotopes.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thus, clumped isotope geochemistry is not concerned with the total number of heavy isotopes in a system, but rather how those heavy isotopes are arranged within the molecules. We do need to know the number of heavy isotopes in the system, though, so we can calculate how many clumps we would expect if they were randomly arranged vs. how many we actually have measured. Then, we can estimate the temperature at which that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule formed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, what is measured is the clumpiness of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas that we get by digesting a carbonate mineral in acid. Common targets are soil carbonates and shells. With a little bit more work (see other projects), we can use the clumpiness we measure to estimate temperatures at or near the surface of the Earth millions of years ago. This thermometer is not based on biology nor does it depend on the isotopic composition of the water from which the mineral grew. That makes for a powerful, quantitative thermometer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing Methods of Clumped Isotope Geochemistry</title>
      <link>/project/clumpy_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/clumpy_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first measurements of ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas evolved from carbonates were published in 2006 by Ghosh et al. While that was over a decade ago, the small size of the ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; signal has ensured that precise and accurate measurements are a challenge. Development and refinement of the method is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/source_cleaning.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Very carefully putting the source back into the MAT 253&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Very carefully putting the source back into the MAT 253
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I jumped into the field in 2014, the biggest challenge was disagreement amongst empirical calibrations of the ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;-temperature relationship. I designed a series of calcite precipitation experiments to address the cause of the discrepancy amongst previously published calibrations. I thought this would be a small side project but it turned into a chapter of my PhD dissertation and a paper in GCA: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these calcite precipitation experiments, myself and others at UW Isolab discovered that the choice of &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O correction parameters was introducing errors into the calculation of ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;. These &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O correction parameters are required to calculate ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; when measured with mass spectrometry (i.e., in all labs making clumped isotope measurements). As a result of this effort, all clumped labs are now using a set of correction parameters recommended by IUPAC (presented in Brand et al., 2010), rather than the parameters from Santrock et al. (1985) that IsoDat (mass spec software) defaulted to. This work resulted in a paper in RCMS:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&lt;/a&gt;. It also provided the motivation for a large, multi-laboratory effort to recalculate previous ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;-temperature empirical calibrations, spearheaded by Sierra Petersen: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These efforts have significantly improved our confidence in the temperatures we estimate from unknown samples. However, methods can always be improved - good isotope geochemistry requires constant vigilance!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward a universal carbonate clumped isotope calibration: Diverse synthesis and preparatory methods suggest a single temperature relationship</title>
      <link>/publication/kelson_etal_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelson_etal_2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choice of 17O correction affects clumped isotope (∆47) values of CO2 measured with mass spectrometry</title>
      <link>/publication/schauer_etal_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schauer_etal_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenhouse climates of the Cenozoic</title>
      <link>/project/greenhouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenhouse/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Globe.png&#34; alt=&#34;Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The late Cretaceous though the early Eocene is an intriguing period of Earth history because of the geologic evidence for globally warm climates that corresponds with high concentrations of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere. Studying these high CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates can  potentially illuminate what high-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates will be like in the future. However, a couple of basic questions about these so-called greenhouse climate regimes drive the paleoclimate research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first, seemingly simple, question is: how hot was it really? One way to quantify earth surface temperatures is by using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates that formed during that time period. I used a seres of stacked paleosols from Big Bend National Park, Texas, USA to estimate air temperatures in the subtropics (30 °N).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SamplingBigYellow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My temperature estimates were intriguingly cold - I estimate summer temperatures of 32 °C, which is not that different from modern summer temperatures in the same place. Either I am interpreting the seasonal bias of my proxy incorrectly &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/project/soil_carbonates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(see other projects)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;   the subtropics were surprisingly cool. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018PA003391&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this project is to determine if greenhouse climates were seasonally equable or not. To answer this, I helped my colleague Landon Burgener in his efforts to compare temperature estimates from a myriad of proxies that likely record different seasonal temperatures. We looked at Cretaceous paleosol deposits in Utah and Montana. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.palaeo.2018.12.004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Utah.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on a late Paleocene to early Eocene record from the Goler Formation in California. This is another stratigraphic record of coastal hothouse climates. There are beautifully preserved oyster shells. Through measuring the clumped and triple oxygen isotopes in these oysters, we&amp;rsquo;re learning about upstream hydrology, temperatures, and paleoaltimetry. More results coming soon here!&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goler1_picture.png&#34; alt=&#34;Eocene oyster shell from the Goler Fm, CA.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Eocene oyster shell from the Goler Fm, CA.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
