<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>modeling on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/tags/modeling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in modeling on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/modeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Goldschmidt 2020 - Virtual presentation</title>
      <link>/project/goldschmidt_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/goldschmidt_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Goldschmidt 2020 Web Display&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goldschmidt.info/2020/abstracts/abstractView?id=2020003403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Abstract: Fingerprinting Soil Water Evaporation with Triple Oxygen Isotopes of Pedogenic Carbonates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julia Kelson, Tyler Huth, Naomi Levin, and Ben Passey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Session 14d: Geochemical indicators of paste climate and environmental change
Monday June 22, 20:06-20:09 (EDT)&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/AIplot.png&#34; alt=&#34;Preliminary data&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Preliminary data
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern soil carbonates</title>
      <link>/project/soil_carbonates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/soil_carbonates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am researching how and when soil carbonates form. This research is necessary in order to use ancient soil carbonates for paleoclimate reconstructions. This research also helps understand how and where inorganic carbon is stored, which has implications for understanding the global carbon cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly assumed that soil carbonates form in the warm season. This assumption is reasonable because the warm season is when plants are growing (and evapo-transpirating), the sun is shining, and the soil is drying out. All of those physical processes should promote supersaturation with respect to calcite.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm.png&#34; alt=&#34;Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, soil carbonates can form in the winter, spring, summer, or fall as well. Environmental factors that control this timing include plant activity, persistent snowpack, soil texture, heavy summer rain, etc.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am using a couple of different approaches to determine when soil carbonates form and how to interpret their isotopic composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106259&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;This paper reviews clumped isotope data on soil carbonates. &lt;/a&gt; The take home: soil carbonate formation temperatures are all over the place! A warm-season bias is the most common, but formation temperatures deviate widely from mean annual air temperatures. We aren&amp;rsquo;t able to explain this variation in formation temperatures easily with environmental data and existing hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I am using a numerical model called HYDRUS-1D to predict the timing of carbonate formation. This work will allow us to delve into individual processes that are impossible to disentangle with empirical data.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HYDRUS.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
