<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 12:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper on the Goler Formation! Can we detect mountains from sea-level, using stable isotopes of oysters?</title>
      <link>/post/goler-paper-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/goler-paper-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited that the first paper from my NSF EAR postdoc fellowship has been accepted for publication in Geology! The initial goal of the project was to reconstruct seasonal variability in temperatures using marine oysters in the Goler Formation. The results turned out a little differently! We measured very light oxygen isotopes, and then started to explore what that would mean for the ancient landscape.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/GolerFig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1 of the paper. Read more here: https://doi.org/10.1130/G49634.1 &#34; width=&#34;700&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Figure 1 of the paper. Read more here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1130/G49634.1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1130/G49634.1&lt;/a&gt;
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field work in Mojave, CA and Jornada, NM</title>
      <link>/post/mojavejornadaoct/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mojavejornadaoct/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Naomi Levin and I continue to launch our CZ17O project studying soil carbonates across dryland ecosystems in the Western US with a trip to the Mojave Desert, California and the Jornada Basin, New Mexico. Both of these sites have monitoring networks that we are fortunate to tap into. We encountered some gorgeous soil carbonates and met with new colleagues who are eager to think about inorganic carbon in soils.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/JTreeAuger.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Augering at the scenic Joshua Tree site in the Mojave Desert&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Augering at the scenic Joshua Tree site in the Mojave Desert
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/flattire.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;We drove many miles and only got one flat tire&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    We drove many miles and only got one flat tire
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/JorGate.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Entrance gate at the Jornada Experimental Range&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Entrance gate at the Jornada Experimental Range
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surgery on the Mass Spec Source</title>
      <link>/post/sourcesurgeryaug2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sourcesurgeryaug2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it takes a whole month just to troubleshoot the mass spectrometer. Due to a long string of hypothesized problems and solutions, a group of IPL-ers collectively took apart and rebuilt the source of the Ny Perspective multiple times this month. Needless to say, we did not generate any usable isotope data during that time. But we did learn about the proper type of scotch-brite to order, and have an improved understanding of the lens stack!&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/source/sourceitself.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;The source of the Nu Perspective, outside of its protective home and in the wild of the laboratory benchtop&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    The source of the Nu Perspective, outside of its protective home and in the wild of the laboratory benchtop
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/source/teamwork.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Natalie and Nick putting the source back together again. Background music: Rush.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Natalie and Nick putting the source back together again. Background music: Rush.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First field work at Reynolds Creek Experimental Watershed, Idaho</title>
      <link>/post/reynoldsaug/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reynoldsaug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Naomi Levin and I had an excellent trip out to Reynolds Creek Experimental Watershed (RCEW), which is a watershed with a long history of monitoring that is part of the newly established Drylands Critical Zone Network. Naomi and I visited to get an early start on our CZ17O project.  We came to collect soil carbonates, soil water samples, set up a precipitation collector, and to connect with our new colleagues at Boise State University and at the USDA. It was so fun to nerd out with other scientists who also love soil carbonates. And oh boy, there were some spectacular soil carbonates to look at!&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Reynolds_crew.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Crew of scientists enjoying a smoky day looking at soils at RCEW&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Crew of scientists enjoying a smoky day looking at soils at RCEW
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fortuitously, a trench had been excavated across some of the dirt roads in the watershed to block access for dust collection. For our purposes, this meant superb exposure of the soils.






&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/ReynoldsTrench.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Happy to see a trench exposing a calcic soil - this is what Naomi and I came here for!&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Happy to see a trench exposing a calcic soil - this is what Naomi and I came here for!
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were also pleased that our plan to auger through gravelly desert soils to collect pristine soil waters actually worked.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Augering_withKyle_small.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;BSU undergraduate Kyle operating the soil auger and Julia trying to keep up with sample labeling  &#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    BSU undergraduate Kyle operating the soil auger and Julia trying to keep up with sample labeling
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soil carbonates in southern Michigan!</title>
      <link>/post/egsrcarbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/egsrcarbs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a gray, rainy, and cold day in October, Tyler Huth and I went on what I thought would be a wild goose chase for secondary soil carbonates in the George Reserve in southern MI, about 20 miles outside of Ann Arbor. We found some spectacular pendants on clasts in a till deposit! We have a lot questions about this carbonate - is it actively dissolving or precipitating? Whats the source of calcium ions? We&amp;rsquo;ll try to get back before the ground freezes to set up some monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/EGSRcarb.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Pendant on a large clast, rock hammer for scale. This was just in the float.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Pendant on a large clast, rock hammer for scale. This was just in the float.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Tydigging.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Ty is stoked to be digging a soil pit in the soft sandy soils in MI&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Ty is stoked to be digging a soil pit in the soft sandy soils in MI
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back in the lab after COVID shutdown</title>
      <link>/post/covid_reopening/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/covid_reopening/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After several months of complete shut down to slow the spread of COVID19, the stable isotope labs at UM are easing into reopening. Homemade masks, gloves, lab coats, and incessant surface sanitizing are the norms. Hoping that we can stay open safely and that the mass spec will cooperate!&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/COVID.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;obligatory masked selfie on my first day back after months&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    obligatory masked selfie on my first day back after months
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper highlighted in Elsevier Special Issue for International Women&#39;s Day</title>
      <link>/post/womensdayhighlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/womensdayhighlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My clumped isotope calibration paper (Kelson et al., 2017) has been chosen to be included in a special issue for International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day 2020. From Elsevier: &amp;ldquo;To mark International Women’s Day 2020, we are proud to promote a selection of recent and highly cited articles from lead female authors, who have published in top Elsevier Earth and Planetary Science journals.  These articles are free to view for 6 months.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/physical-sciences-and-engineering/earth-and-planetary-sciences/journals/international-womens-day?utm_campaign=STMJ_108700_SISSUE&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_dgroup=108700_MAIN_NOAB_SGL_ALL&amp;amp;utm_acid=180503095&amp;amp;SIS_ID=1148&amp;amp;dgcid=STMJ_108700_SISSUE&amp;amp;CMX_ID=ECR-1148&amp;amp;utm_in=DM657477&amp;amp;utm_source=AC_30&amp;amp;utm_term=108700_SISSUE_MAIN_NOAB_SINGLE_ALL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Access the special issue with this link.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Started NSF-EAR postdoc in Ann Arbor, MI</title>
      <link>/post/arrived_mi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/arrived_mi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I arrived in MI and joined Sierra Petersen&amp;rsquo;s SCIPP (Stable and Clumped Isotopes for Paleoclimate &amp;amp; Paleoceanography) group. With two postdocs, 5 graduate students, and 3 undergrads, the lab feels like an active and exciting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, I&amp;rsquo;ll be working on Sierra&amp;rsquo;s new Nu instrument. The Nu allows for smaller sample sizes for clumped isotope analyses. Hopefully this will allow me to micro-sample shell and resolve seasonal variations in temperature. Also I&amp;rsquo;ll be working with IsoPaleoLab (Levin/Passey lab) to measure triple oxygen isotopes in carbonates with the goal of quantifying aridity in greenhouse climates.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SCIPP_group.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Portrait of the SCIPPers in Sierra&amp;#39;s backyard&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Portrait of the SCIPPers in Sierra&amp;rsquo;s backyard
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, former labmate Mike T took me to the Big House to see my first college football game. The UM school spirit is truly exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/BigHouse.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I think Michigan won?&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    I think Michigan won?
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer travels</title>
      <link>/post/summer_travels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/summer_travels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maybe most academics don&amp;rsquo;t take long vacations, but I am taking this summer off! The flexibility in postdoc-start-date allowed me to take a break after graduating from UW in June. So, what am I doing with my time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will mostly be in Copenhagen, Denmark, exploring Scandinavian craft beer, swimming in the canals, going for bike rides, and finishing manuscripts from my PhD work. I also plan to travel to Italy, Norway, Czechia, and Sweden. Then I&amp;rsquo;ll head back to North America for a backpacking trip in the Sierra and a sea kayaking trip in British Columbia before driving eastward to my new basecamp in Ann Arbor.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Steno.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Did you know Steno was Danish?&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Did you know Steno was Danish?
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/bikes_CPH.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Endless bikes at the bike rack in central station, CPH.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Endless bikes at the bike rack in central station, CPH.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Tuborg_CPH.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Not quite a craft beer...&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Not quite a craft beer&amp;hellip;
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at UW Earth &amp; Space Science Graduation</title>
      <link>/post/uw_ess_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/uw_ess_graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;UW Earth and Space Sciences graduation really started off right - with a fire alarm! The alarm went off just when the chair, Ken Creager, was trying to get the ceremony started. Everyone evacuated, waited for the fire department to ascertain that there was not actually a fire, then we re-started the ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/doorway_grad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Goofing around with Mike Turzewski (fellow grad) and  Kate Huntington (my advisor). &#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Goofing around with Mike Turzewski (fellow grad) and  Kate Huntington (my advisor).
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, I was honored to give the graduation speech.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/speaking_at_grad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Best outfit to give a talk in ever.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Best outfit to give a talk in ever.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nicole Sarieddine presents at Undergrad Research Symposium</title>
      <link>/post/nicole_mgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nicole_mgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nicole culminated her 2 years of undergraduate research with a presentation at the UW Undergraduate Research Symposium. She worked on a slough of projects relating to the climate reconstructions using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates. At this symposium, she presented results on using remotely-sensed soil moisture data to predict when soil carbonates form in North America. The jury is still out on whether or not remotely sensed soil moisture data is actually useful for this application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
