<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 12:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Started NSF-EAR postdoc in Ann Arbor, MI</title>
      <link>/post/arrived_mi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/arrived_mi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I arrived in MI and joined Sierra Petersen&amp;rsquo;s SCIPP (Stable and Clumped Isotopes for Paleoclimate &amp;amp; Paleoceanography) group. With two postdocs, 5 graduate students, and 3 undergrads, the lab feels like an active and exciting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my postdoc work, I&amp;rsquo;ll be working on Sierra&amp;rsquo;s new Nu instrument, which allows for smaller sample sizes for clumped isotope analyses. Hopefully this will allow me to micro-sample shell and resolve seasonal variations in temperature. Also I&amp;rsquo;ll be working with IsoPaleoLab (Levin/Passey lab) to measure triple oxygen isotopes in carbonates and hopefully learn about aridity in greenhouse climates.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SCIPP_group.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Portrait of the SCIPPers in Sierra&amp;#39;s backyard&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Portrait of the SCIPPers in Sierra&amp;rsquo;s backyard
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, former labmate Mike T took me to the Big House to see my first college football game. The UM school spirit is truly exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/BigHouse.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I think Michigan won?&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    I think Michigan won?
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer travels</title>
      <link>/post/summer_travels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/summer_travels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maybe most academics don&amp;rsquo;t take long vacations, but I am taking this summer off! The flexibility in postdoc-start-date allowed me to take a break after graduating from UW in June. So, what am I doing with my time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will mostly be in Copenhagen, Denmark, exploring Scandinavian craft beer, swimming in the canals, going for bike rides, and finishing manuscripts from my PhD work. I also plan to travel to Italy, Norway, Czechia, and Sweden. Then I&amp;rsquo;ll head back to North America for a backpacking trip in the Sierra and a sea kayaking trip in British Columbia before driving eastward to my new basecamp in Ann Arbor.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Steno.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Did you know Steno was Danish?&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Did you know Steno was Danish?
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/bikes_CPH.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Endless bikes at the bike rack in central station, CPH.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Endless bikes at the bike rack in central station, CPH.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Tuborg_CPH.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Not quite a craft beer...&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Not quite a craft beer&amp;hellip;
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at UW Earth &amp; Space Science Graduation</title>
      <link>/post/uw_ess_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/uw_ess_graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;UW Earth and Space Sciences graduation really started off right - with a fire alarm! The alarm went off just when the chair, Ken Creager, was trying to get the ceremony started. Everyone evacuated, waited for the fire department to ascertain that there was not actually a fire, then we re-started the ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/doorway_grad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Goofing around with Mike Turzewski (fellow grad) and  Kate Huntington (my advisor). &#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Goofing around with Mike Turzewski (fellow grad) and  Kate Huntington (my advisor).
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, I was honored to give the graduation speech.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/speaking_at_grad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Best outfit to give a talk in ever.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Best outfit to give a talk in ever.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nicole Sarieddine presents at Undergrad Research Symposium</title>
      <link>/post/nicole_mgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nicole_mgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nicole culminated her 2 years of undergraduate research with a presentation at the UW Undergraduate Research Symposium. She worked on a slough of projects relating to the climate reconstructions using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates. At this symposium, she presented results on using remotely-sensed soil moisture data to predict when soil carbonates form in North America. The jury is still out on whether or not remotely sensed soil moisture data is actually useful for this application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
