<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Goldschmidt 2020 - Virtual presentation</title>
      <link>/project/goldschmidt_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/goldschmidt_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Goldschmidt 2020 Web Display&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goldschmidt.info/2020/abstracts/abstractView?id=2020003403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Abstract: Fingerprinting Soil Water Evaporation with Triple Oxygen Isotopes of Pedogenic Carbonates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julia Kelson, Tyler Huth, Naomi Levin, and Ben Passey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Session 14d: Geochemical indicators of paste climate and environmental change
Monday June 22, 20:06-20:09 (EDT)&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goldschmidt/AIplot.png&#34; alt=&#34;Preliminary data&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Preliminary data
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern soil carbonates</title>
      <link>/project/soil_carbonates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/soil_carbonates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am researching how and when soil carbonates form. This research is necessary in order to use ancient soil carbonates for paleoclimate reconstructions. This research also helps understand how and where inorganic carbon is stored, which has implications for understanding the global carbon cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly assumed that soil carbonates form in the warm season. This assumption is reasonable because the warm season is when plants are growing (and evapo-transpirating), the sun is shining, and the soil is drying out. All of those physical processes should promote supersaturation with respect to calcite.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm.png&#34; alt=&#34;Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, soil carbonates can form in the winter, spring, summer, or fall as well. Environmental factors that control this timing include plant activity, persistent snowpack, soil texture, heavy summer rain, etc.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am using a couple of different approaches to determine when soil carbonates form and how to interpret their isotopic composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106259&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;This paper reviews clumped isotope data on soil carbonates. &lt;/a&gt; The take home: soil carbonate formation temperatures are all over the place! A warm-season bias is the most common, but formation temperatures deviate widely from mean annual air temperatures. We aren&amp;rsquo;t able to explain this variation in formation temperatures easily with environmental data and existing hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I am using a numerical model called HYDRUS-1D to predict the timing of carbonate formation. This work will allow us to delve into individual processes that are impossible to disentangle with empirical data.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HYDRUS.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sediment Fingerprinting</title>
      <link>/project/sed_fingerprinting_or/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sed_fingerprinting_or/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am interested in applying my geochemistry skills to problems in sediment transport and landscape evolution on human timescales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, took advantage of an NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program offshoot called GRIP (Graduate Research Internship Program) (alphabet soup) to spend about three months working at the USGS Water Science Center in Portland, Oregon. My task was to figure out if it would be possible to use the chemical composition, or &amp;lsquo;fingerprint,&amp;rsquo; of sediment to trace where in a watershed the phosphorous-rich sediment comes from.  The river of interest, the Sprague River, has a long, complicated history of conflict between ranchers, native populations, and environmental regulators.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Sprague/trampled.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Banks trampled by cows and fencing across the river. Not difficult to imagine an unnatural source of sediment here.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Banks trampled by cows and fencing across the river. Not difficult to imagine an unnatural source of sediment here.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing the Methods of Clumped Isotope Geochemistry</title>
      <link>/project/clumpy_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/clumpy_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first measurements of ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas evolved from carbonates were published in 2006 by Ghosh et al. While that was over a decade ago, the small size of the ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; signal has ensured that precise and accurate measurements are a challenge. Development and refinement of the method is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/source_cleaning.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Very carefully putting the source back into the MAT 253&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Very carefully putting the source back into the MAT 253
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I jumped into the field in 2014, the biggest challenge was disagreement amongst empirical calibrations of the ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;-temperature relationship. I designed a series of calcite precipitation experiments to address the cause of the discrepancy amongst previously published calibrations. I thought this would be a small side project but it turned into a chapter of my PhD dissertation and a paper in GCA: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2016.10.010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these calcite precipitation experiments, myself and others at UW Isolab discovered that the choice of &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O correction parameters was introducing errors into the calculation of ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;. These &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;O correction parameters are required to calculate ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt; when measured with mass spectrometry (i.e., in all labs making clumped isotope measurements). As a result of this effort, all clumped labs are now using a set of correction parameters recommended by IUPAC (presented in Brand et al., 2010), rather than the parameters from Santrock et al. (1985) that IsoDat (mass spec software) defaulted to. This work resulted in a paper in RCMS:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7743&lt;/a&gt;. It also provided the motivation for a large, multi-laboratory effort to recalculate previous ∆&lt;sub&gt;47&lt;/sub&gt;-temperature empirical calibrations, spearheaded by Sierra Petersen: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GC008127&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These efforts have significantly improved our confidence in the temperatures we estimate from unknown samples. However, methods can always be improved - good isotope geochemistry requires constant vigilance!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenhouse climates of the Cenozoic</title>
      <link>/project/greenhouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenhouse/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Globe.png&#34; alt=&#34;Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The late Cretaceous though the early Eocene is an intriguing period of Earth history because of the geologic evidence for globally warm climates that corresponds with high concentrations of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere. Studying these high CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates can  potentially illuminate what high-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates will be like in the future. However, a couple of basic questions about these so-called greenhouse climate regimes drive the paleoclimate research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first, seemingly simple, question is: how hot was it really? One way to quantify earth surface temperatures is by using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates that formed during that time period. I used a seres of stacked paleosols from Big Bend National Park, Texas, USA to estimate air temperatures in the subtropics (30 °N).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SamplingBigYellow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My temperature estimates were intriguingly cold - I estimate summer temperatures of 32 °C, which is not that different from modern summer temperatures in the same place. Either I am interpreting the seasonal bias of my proxy incorrectly &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/project/soil_carbonates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(see other projects)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;   the subtropics were surprisingly cool. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018PA003391&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this project is to determine if greenhouse climates were seasonally equable or not. To answer this, I helped my colleague Landon Burgener in his efforts to compare temperature estimates from a myriad of proxies that likely record different seasonal temperatures. We looked at Cretaceous paleosol deposits in Utah and Montana. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.palaeo.2018.12.004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Utah.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m actively working on a late Paleocene to early Eocene record from the Goler Formation in California. This is another near coastal section that fortunately has a variety of carbonates to work with - including oyster shells.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hobbies</title>
      <link>/project/personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/personal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I try to balance work with some life&amp;hellip; Here&amp;rsquo;s a smattering of what I get up to.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/Trudging_up_Muir_PC_SeanLahusen.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Skinning on Mt Rainier, with Mt. Adams chillin in the background. PC Sean Lahusen&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Skinning on Mt Rainier, with Mt. Adams chillin in the background. PC Sean Lahusen
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/canoe.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Building a skin-on-frame canoe. The boat kind of looks like it would float in this picture.&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Building a skin-on-frame canoe. The boat kind of looks like it would float in this picture.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/Are_we_in_theBC_GlacierPeakW.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Have we reached the backcountry yet? Glacier Peak Wilderness, WA. PC Todd Anderson&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Have we reached the backcountry yet? Glacier Peak Wilderness, WA. PC Todd Anderson
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/IMG_9330.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I&amp;#39;m usually happiest when I&amp;#39;m in glaciated landscapes, but that is not really a feasible place to live. Here I&amp;#39;m goofing off with my sister Suzanne in Norway.&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    I&amp;rsquo;m usually happiest when I&amp;rsquo;m in glaciated landscapes, but that is not really a feasible place to live. Here I&amp;rsquo;m goofing off with my sister Suzanne in Norway.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/Skiing_InspirationGlacier.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Learning how to ski with a heavy pack on the Inspiration Glacier, North Cascades, WA. PC David Lilien&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Learning how to ski with a heavy pack on the Inspiration Glacier, North Cascades, WA. PC David Lilien
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;








&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/outdoors/DeceptionPass_crop.png&#34; alt=&#34;Finishing the Deception Pass 50k, Anacortes, WA, December 2018&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Finishing the Deception Pass 50k, Anacortes, WA, December 2018
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
