<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>paleosols on Julia Kelson</title>
    <link>/tags/paleosols/</link>
    <description>Recent content in paleosols on Julia Kelson</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/paleosols/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CZ17O: Triple Oxygen Isotopes in Soil Carbonates</title>
      <link>/project/cz17o/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cz17o/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Soils are key to understanding climate change in drylands given their importance in mediating the flux of both water and carbon. Pedogenic carbonates underly dryland soils and provide essential ground-level perspectives on climate change through geologic time and in the present. However, pedogenic carbonates currently fall short as tracers of water and carbon fluxes because we have an incomplete understanding of how they form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address the gap in our understanding of how soil carbonates form, my collaborator Naomi Levin and I are using triple oxygen isotope geochemistry (&lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/primer/tripleoprimer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;primer here&lt;/a&gt;) to directly assess the importance of evaporation during soil carbonate formation. We&amp;rsquo;re considering how and where biotic processes (root water uptake/transpiration) vs abiotic processes (evaporation) dominate soil carbonate formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working across aridity gradients in North America, specifically targeting two sites that are a part of the Drylands Critical Zone Network - Jornada, New Mexico, and Reynolds Creek, Idaho. Our driest soils sites are in the Mojave National Preserve which has an incredible network of above- and below- ground monitoring sites set up by our collaborator Ron Amundson (UC Berkeley).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/AImap_v3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Study sites take advantage of the natural gradient in aridity in the Western US.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Study sites take advantage of the natural gradient in aridity in the Western US.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is just the start of an NSF-funded two year project! So far, the project has been an awesome way to connect with collaborators who also love soils, isotopes, and drylands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preliminary data that provided the basis for our successful NSF proposal is described in my &lt;a href=&#34;(https://jrkelson.github.io/project/goldschmidt_2020/)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Goldschmidt presentation from 2020&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Bk_horizon_Reynolds.png&#34; alt=&#34;A beautiful calcic horizon exposed in an open trench at the Lower Sheep site in Reynolds Creek, Idaho.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    A beautiful calcic horizon exposed in an open trench at the Lower Sheep site in Reynolds Creek, Idaho.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonality of soil carbonate formation</title>
      <link>/project/soil_carbonates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/soil_carbonates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When do soil carbonates form? We need to be able to answer this question in order to use ancient soil carbonates for paleoclimate reconstructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly assumed that soil carbonates form in the warm season. This assumption is reasonable because the warm season is when plants are growing (and evapo-transpirating), the sun is shining, and the soil is drying out. All of those physical processes should promote supersaturation with respect to calcite.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm.png&#34; alt=&#34;Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Yellow arrows indicate carbonate formation (nodules and pendants). Illustration help from Landon Burgener.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;BUT soil carbonates can form in the winter, spring, summer, or fall. Environmental factors that control this timing include plant activity, persistent snowpack, soil texture, heavy summer rain, etc.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/CarbForm2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Environmental factors that can change the timing of carbonate formation.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am using multiple approaches to determine when soil carbonates form and how to interpret their isotopic composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106259&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;First, this paper reviews clumped isotope data on soil carbonates. &lt;/a&gt; Clumped isotope-based temperatures can reveal apparent seasonal biases in modern soil carbonates. The take home: soil carbonate formation temperatures are all over the place! A warm-season bias is the most common, but formation temperatures deviate widely from mean annual air temperatures. We aren&amp;rsquo;t able to explain this variation in formation temperatures easily with environmental data and existing hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I am using a numerical model called HYDRUS-1D to predict the timing of carbonate formation. This work will allow us to delve into individual processes that are impossible to disentangle with empirical data.&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HYDRUS.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenhouse climates of the Cenozoic</title>
      <link>/project/greenhouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/greenhouse/</guid>
      <description>





&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Globe.png&#34; alt=&#34;Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Reptile and palm fossils at the poles indicate warm climates.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The late Cretaceous though the early Eocene is an intriguing period of Earth history because of the geologic evidence for globally warm climates that corresponds with high concentrations of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere. Studying these high CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates can  potentially illuminate what high-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; climates will be like in the future. However, a couple of basic questions about these so-called greenhouse climate regimes drive the paleoclimate research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first, seemingly simple, question is: how hot was it really? One way to quantify earth surface temperatures is by using the clumped isotope composition of soil carbonates that formed during that time period. I used a seres of stacked paleosols from Big Bend National Park, Texas, USA to estimate air temperatures in the subtropics (30 °N).&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/SamplingBigYellow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Sampling the Hannold Hill Formation in the heat.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My temperature estimates were intriguingly cold - I estimate summer temperatures of 32 °C, which is not that different from modern summer temperatures in the same place. Either I am interpreting the seasonal bias of my proxy incorrectly &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrkelson.github.io/project/soil_carbonates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(see other projects)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;   the subtropics were surprisingly cool. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2018PA003391&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this project is to determine if greenhouse climates were seasonally equable or not. To answer this, I helped my colleague Landon Burgener in his efforts to compare temperature estimates from a myriad of proxies that likely record different seasonal temperatures. We looked at Cretaceous paleosol deposits in Utah and Montana. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.palaeo.2018.12.004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publication here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Utah.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Field work in the Kaiparowits Formation, Utah.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on a late Paleocene to early Eocene record from the Goler Formation in California. This is another stratigraphic record of coastal hothouse climates. There are beautifully preserved oyster shells. Through measuring the clumped and triple oxygen isotopes in these oysters, I&amp;rsquo;m learning about upstream hydrology, temperatures, and paleoaltimetry. More results coming soon here!&lt;/p&gt;







&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Goler1_picture.png&#34; alt=&#34;Eocene oyster shell from the Goler Fm, CA.&#34; &gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Eocene oyster shell from the Goler Fm, CA.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
